<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <cosponsors />
    <notes />
    <titles>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>RESPECT Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Requirements, Expectations, and Standard Procedures for Executive Consultation with Tribes Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>To prescribe procedures for effective consultation and coordination by Federal agencies with federally recognized Indian tribes regarding Federal Government activities that impact tribal lands and interests to ensure that meaningful tribal input is an integral part of the Federal decisionmaking process.</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>RESPECT Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <originChamber>House</originChamber>
    <actions>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <prayer>1</prayer>
        <placeholderTextForH>1</placeholderTextForH>
        <introducedInTheHouse>1</introducedInTheHouse>
        <billReferrals>1</billReferrals>
        <introducedInHouse>1</introducedInHouse>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-06-14</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Indian, Insular and Alaska Native Affairs Subcommittee</name>
          <systemCode>hsii24</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>House committee actions</name>
          <code>1</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Subcommittee Hearings Held.</text>
        <type>Committee</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-06-07</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Indian, Insular and Alaska Native Affairs Subcommittee</name>
          <systemCode>hsii24</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>House committee actions</name>
          <code>1</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Indian, Insular and Alaska Native Affairs.</text>
        <type>Committee</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>H11100</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>House floor actions</name>
          <code>2</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee>
          <name>Natural Resources Committee</name>
          <systemCode>hsii00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2016-06-03</actionDate>
        <text>Referred to the House Committee on Natural Resources.</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>Intro-H</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2016-06-03</actionDate>
        <text>Introduced in House</text>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>1000</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2016-06-03</actionDate>
        <text>Introduced in House</text>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <houseOfRepresentatives>5</houseOfRepresentatives>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:05:20Z</updateDate>
    <billNumber>5379</billNumber>
    <latestAction>
      <text>Subcommittee Hearings Held.</text>
      <actionDate>2016-06-14</actionDate>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <version>1.0.0</version>
    <introducedDate>2016-06-03</introducedDate>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1708</lisID>
          <gpoId>7804</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>G000551</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <party>D</party>
        <bioguideId>G000551</bioguideId>
        <state>AZ</state>
        <firstName>Raul</firstName>
        <lastName>Grijalva</lastName>
        <middleName>M.</middleName>
        <district>3</district>
        <fullName>Rep. Grijalva, Raul M. [D-AZ-3]</fullName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <billType>HR</billType>
    <createDate>2016-06-04T04:50:37Z</createDate>
    <relatedBills />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative remedies</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Federal-Indian relations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Indian lands and resources rights</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Judicial review and appeals</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Licensing and registrations</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Native Americans</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <constitutionalAuthorityStatementText><![CDATA[<pre>From the Congressional Record Online through the Government Publishing Office [<a href='http://www.gpo.gov'>www.gpo.gov</a>]By Mr. GRIJALVA:H.R. 5379.Congress has the power to enact this legislation pursuantto the following:U.S. Const. art. I, Sec. 8, c1. 3.[Page H3462]</pre>]]></constitutionalAuthorityStatementText>
    <title>RESPECT Act</title>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><strong>Requirements, Expectations, and Standard Procedures for Executive Consultation with Tribes Act or the RESPECT Act</strong></p> <p>This bill requires federal agencies to: (1) have an accountable process to ensure meaningful and timely input by Indian tribes before undertaking any activity that may have substantial direct impacts on the lands or interests of such tribes, on the relationship between the federal government and such tribes, or on the distribution of power and responsibilities between the government and such tribes; and (2) consult with Indian tribes concerning all activities that would affect any federal land that shares a border with Indian country. An agency may temporarily waive such requirements in an emergency area during an emergency period. </p> <p>Such consultation must be completed before any federal funds are expended for the activity and before the issuance of any license other than for funding nondestructive project planning activities. </p> <p>An agency shall: </p> <ul> <li>compile a draft of the scope of a project, including any anticipated tribal impacts, as early as possible in the planning stage of an activity; </li> <li>mail a copy of the planning document and a letter requesting consultation meetings to the relevant tribal government officials and non-tribal stakeholders and, at an affected tribe's request, to nongovernmental tribal stakeholders; </li> <li>negotiate consultation meeting arrangements with the affected tribes; </li> <li>execute a memorandum agreement of the scope of consultation or, upon determining that further consultation will not be productive, terminate consultation and proceed to decision stage procedures; </li> <li>compile, mail to affected tribal governments, and publish a document consisting of the plan for the activity and its anticipated tribal impacts; </li> <li>allow 90 days for comments on such document; </li> <li>after such 90-day period, publish and mail to affected tribes a preliminary decision letter stating the decision to proceed or not proceed with the activity, the decision's rationale, changes made in response to comments, and points where the decision conflicts with the expressed requests of affected tribes; </li> <li>60 days after issuing such letter, notify the affected tribal governments of the agency's final decision; and </li> <li>keep an official consultation record. </li></ul> <p>Each agency shall designate an official who shall: (1) have principal responsibility for reviewing existing consultation procedures and for implementation of this bill, and (2) submit to the Office of Management and Budget a description of the agency's revised consultation process.</p> <p>The bill requires federal agencies to: (1) recognize and respect Indian tribal self-government and sovereignty, honor tribal treaty and other rights, and strive to meet the responsibilities that arise from the unique legal relationship between the federal government and tribal governments; (2) grant Indian tribal governments the maximum discretion possible in the administration of federal statutes and regulations; (3) take steps to streamline the processes under which Indian tribes apply for waivers of statutory and regulatory requirements; and (4) consider any such waiver application in connection with any agency program with a general view toward increasing opportunities for utilizing flexible policy approaches at the Indian tribal level.</p> <p>An Indian tribe may seek judicial review of a determination of an agency under this bill in accordance with the Administrative Procedure Act if the tribe has exhausted all other administrative remedies available to it.</p>]]></text>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2016-09-30T20:12:52Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <name>Introduced in House</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDate>2016-06-03</actionDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in House</actionDesc>
          <updateDate>2016-06-03T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Native Americans</name>
    </policyArea>
    <laws />
    <recordedVotes />
    <congress>114</congress>
    <amendments />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <subcommittees>
            <item>
              <activities>
                <item>
                  <name>Hearings by</name>
                  <date>2016-06-14T16:21:05Z</date>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <name>Referred to</name>
                  <date>2016-06-07T21:25:09Z</date>
                </item>
              </activities>
              <name>Indian, Insular and Alaska Native Affairs Subcommittee</name>
              <systemCode>hsii24</systemCode>
            </item>
          </subcommittees>
          <systemCode>hsii00</systemCode>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <chamber>House</chamber>
          <name>Natural Resources Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2016-06-03T20:30:13Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

