<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <recordedVotes />
    <titles>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>Cyber AIR Act</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>Cybersecurity Standards for Aircraft to Improve Resilience Act of 2016</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>A bill to require the disclosure of information relating to cyberattacks on aircraft systems and maintenance and ground support systems for aircraft, to identify and address cybersecurity vulnerabilities to the United States commercial aviation system, and for other purposes.</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>Cyber AIR Act</title>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <actions>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-04-07</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-04-07</actionDate>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee />
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <links />
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
    </policyArea>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <cosponsors />
    <introducedDate>2016-04-07</introducedDate>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2016-04-07</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <billNumber>2764</billNumber>
    <amendments />
    <laws />
    <createDate>2016-04-08T04:35:03Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <title>Cyber AIR Act</title>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2016-05-26T18:02:51Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><strong>Cybersecurity Standards for Aircraft to Improve Resilience Act of 2016 or the Cyber AIR Act</strong></p> <p>This bill directs the Department of Transportation (DOT) to require domestic or foreign air carriers and manufacturers of aircraft or electronic control, communications, maintenance, or ground support systems for aircraft to disclose to the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) any attempted or successful cyberattack against any system on board an aircraft or against any maintenance or ground support system for aircraft.</p> <p>The FAA shall use the information obtained through such disclosures to: (1) improve the regulations (to be prescribed by DOT) to incorporate requirements relating to cybersecurity into the requirements for obtaining an air carrier operating certificate or a production certificate; and (2) notify air carriers, aircraft manufacturers, and other federal agencies of cybersecurity vulnerabilities in systems on board an aircraft or maintenance or ground support systems for aircraft. </p> <p>In prescribing such regulations, DOT must require: (1) all entry points to the electronic systems of each aircraft operating in U.S. airspace and maintenance or ground support systems for such aircraft to be equipped with reasonable measures to protect against cyberattacks; and (2) the periodic evaluation of, and updates to, such measures for security vulnerabilities using best security practices.</p> <p>The FAA must report to Congress annually on attempted and successful cyberattacks against any system on board an aircraft and against maintenance or ground support systems for aircraft.</p> <p>The Commercial Aviation Communications Safety and Security Leadership Group shall: (1) be responsible for evaluating the cybersecurity vulnerabilities of certain broadband wireless communications equipment designed for consumer use on board aircraft; and (2) require the implementation by air carriers, manufacturers, and communications service providers of technical and operational security measures it deems necessary to prevent cyberattacks that exploit such equipment.</p>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2016-04-07T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDate>2016-04-07</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <relatedBills />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2016-04-07T20:15:44Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:11:01Z</updateDate>
    <congress>114</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Aviation and airports</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Computer security and identity theft</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Transportation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Telephone and wireless communication</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation safety and security</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <notes />
    <billType>S</billType>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Sen. Markey, Edward J. [D-MA]</fullName>
        <byRequestType />
        <party>D</party>
        <lastName>MARKEY</lastName>
        <firstName>EDWARD</firstName>
        <bioguideId>M000133</bioguideId>
        <middleName>J.</middleName>
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>7972</gpoId>
          <lisID>735</lisID>
          <bioguideId>M000133</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <state>MA</state>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <version>1.0.0</version>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

