<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <recordedVotes />
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-07-22</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>hswm01</systemCode>
          <name>Social Security Subcommittee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>1</code>
          <name>House committee actions</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Social Security.</text>
        <type>Committee</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-07-18</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>hswm00</systemCode>
          <name>Ways and Means Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>2</code>
          <name>House floor actions</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Referred to the House Committee on Ways and Means.</text>
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>H11100</actionCode>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-07-18</actionDate>
        <committee />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Introduced in House</text>
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>Intro-H</actionCode>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-07-18</actionDate>
        <committee />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Introduced in House</text>
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>1000</actionCode>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <billReferrals>1</billReferrals>
        <introducedInHouse>1</introducedInHouse>
        <placeholderTextForH>1</placeholderTextForH>
        <introducedInTheHouse>1</introducedInTheHouse>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <actionByCounts>
        <houseOfRepresentatives>4</houseOfRepresentatives>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Social Welfare</name>
    </policyArea>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <cosponsors />
    <introducedDate>2016-07-18</introducedDate>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2016-07-22</actionDate>
      <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Social Security.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <billNumber>5919</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Preserving and Reforming SSDI (PAR-SSDI) Act of 2016</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>To amend title II of the Social Security Act to improve the process by which the Social Security Administration makes disability determinations and awards disability benefits, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Preserving and Reforming SSDI (PAR-SSDI) Act of 2016</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <amendments />
    <laws />
    <originChamber>House</originChamber>
    <constitutionalAuthorityStatementText><![CDATA[<pre>From the Congressional Record Online through the Government Publishing Office [<a href='http://www.gpo.gov'>www.gpo.gov</a>]By Mr. SCHWEIKERT:H.R. 5919.Congress has the power to enact this legislation pursuantto the following:Article I, Section 8, Clause 1____________________[Page H5023]</pre>]]></constitutionalAuthorityStatementText>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <title>Preserving and Reforming SSDI (PAR-SSDI) Act of 2016</title>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in House</actionDesc>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><b>Preserving and Reforming SSDI (PAR-SSDI) Act of 2016</b></p> <p>This bill amends title II (Old Age, Survivors and Disability Insurance) (OASDI) of the Social Security Act (SSAct) to:</p> <ul> <li>direct the Social Security Administration (SSA), in determining whether an individual is under a disability, to make such a determination without regard to the individual's ability to communicate in English;</li> <li>prohibit the SSA, in determining whether an individual is under a disability for a month, from considering the individual's vocational background in computing the quarters of coverage requirement unless the individual had not less than 16 quarters of coverage during the 24-quarter period ending with the quarter in which such month occurs; and</li> <li>direct the SSA to prepare and implement a complete update of the vocational and educational factors considered in making disability determinations.</li> </ul> <p>The bill declares that for any week in whole or in part within a month that an individual is paid or determined to be eligible for unemployment compensation he or she shall be deemed to have engaged in substantial gainful activity and so be disqualified from receiving Social Security disability benefits after a certain period has elapsed.</p> <p>The bill also states that, for purposes of determining services rendered by an individual during a period of trial work which will not disqualify the individual for disability benefits, the individual shall be deemed to have rendered services in a month if he or she is entitled to unemployment compensation or trade adjustment assistance for that month.</p> <p>The bill revises prerequisites for the entitlement of certain individuals under age 65 to SSAct title XVIII (Medicare) part A hospital insurance benefits. The length of time such an individual must be entitled to disability insurance, child's insurance, or widow's insurance benefits, in order to qualify for entitlement to Medicare part A hospital benefits, shall increase from the current 24 months to 60 months.</p> <p>If the amount of an individual's unearned income for a month is equal to or greater than the monthly income limit for that month, the individual shall be deemed to have engaged in substantial gainful activity for the month for purposes of determining disability insurance benefit payments.</p> <p>The SSA must receive from an individual and/or the individual's representative, in its entirety and without redaction, all known relevant medical evidence related to a disability claim. Any medical evidence not submitted in its entirety or not furnished by a licensed practitioner shall be excluded in disability determinations.</p> <p>In determining whether a disability benefits applicant is disabled, the SSA shall not consider medical evidence resulting from a consultative exam with a health care provider unless the application is accompanied by a Medical Consultant Acknowledgment Form signed by the health care provider who conducted the exam.</p> <p>The bill changes the index used to calculate OASDI cost-of-living adjustments to the Chained Price Index for All Urban Consumers.</p> <p>In any case in which SSA initiates a review of disability benefits for an individual, the review shall include an independent estimate by a qualified Social Security income verification contractor of the individual's monthly income.</p>]]></text>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2016-08-01T14:45:33Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <updateDate>2016-07-18T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <actionDate>2016-07-18</actionDate>
          <name>Introduced in House</name>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <number>918</number>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>114</congress>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Referred to the Subcommittee on Social Security.</text>
          <actionDate>2015-02-27</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <latestTitle>Social Security Disability Insurance and Unemployment Benefits Double Dip Elimination Act</latestTitle>
      </item>
      <item>
        <number>499</number>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>114</congress>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Finance.</text>
          <actionDate>2015-02-12</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
        <type>S</type>
        <latestTitle>Social Security Disability Insurance and Unemployment Benefits Double Dip Elimination Act</latestTitle>
      </item>
      <item>
        <number>2005</number>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <congress>114</congress>
        <latestAction>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Finance.</text>
          <actionDate>2015-08-06</actionDate>
        </latestAction>
        <type>S</type>
        <latestTitle>Social Security Disability Insurance and Unemployment Benefits Double Dip Elimination Act</latestTitle>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <billType>HR</billType>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <name>Ways and Means Committee</name>
          <subcommittees>
            <item>
              <name>Social Security Subcommittee</name>
              <activities>
                <item>
                  <date>2016-07-22T16:28:48Z</date>
                  <name>Referred to</name>
                </item>
              </activities>
              <systemCode>hswm01</systemCode>
            </item>
          </subcommittees>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2016-07-18T18:30:38Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <chamber>House</chamber>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <systemCode>hswm00</systemCode>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:05:55Z</updateDate>
    <congress>114</congress>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Social Welfare</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Disability assistance</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Foreign language and bilingual programs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Hospital care</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Inflation and prices</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Medical tests and diagnostic methods</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Medicare</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Social security and elderly assistance</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Trade adjustment assistance</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Unemployment</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <notes />
    <createDate>2016-07-19T14:13:34Z</createDate>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <fullName>Rep. Schweikert, David [R-AZ-6]</fullName>
        <state>AZ</state>
        <byRequestType />
        <party>R</party>
        <lastName>Schweikert</lastName>
        <firstName>David</firstName>
        <bioguideId>S001183</bioguideId>
        <middleName />
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>S001183</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>7802</gpoId>
          <lisID>1994</lisID>
        </identifiers>
        <district>6</district>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <version>1.0.0</version>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

