<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <recordedVotes />
    <updateDate>2016-10-25T16:32:06Z</updateDate>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Open Book on Equal Access to Justice Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>A bill to amend titles 5 and 28, United States Code, to require annual reports to Congress on, and the maintenance of databases on, awards of fees and other expenses to prevailing parties in certain administrative proceedings and court cases to which the United States is a party, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Open Book on Equal Access to Justice Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <lastName>Walsh</lastName>
        <firstName>John</firstName>
        <bioguideId>W000818</bioguideId>
        <middleName>E.</middleName>
        <state>MT</state>
        <fullName>Sen. Walsh, John E. [D-MT]</fullName>
        <party>D</party>
        <byRequestType />
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>W000818</bioguideId>
          <gpoId />
          <lisID>2198</lisID>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <introducedDate>2014-07-31</introducedDate>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2014-08-19T15:30:21Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <updateDate>2014-07-31T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
          <text><![CDATA[Open Book on Equal Access to Justice Act - Amends the Equal Access to Justice Act and the federal judicial code to require the Chairman of the Administrative Conference of the United States to submit to Congress and make publicly available on an Internet website an annual report on the amount of fees and other expenses awarded to prevailing parties other than the United States in certain administrative proceedings and civil action court cases (excluding tort cases) to which the United States is a party, including settlement agreements. <p>Requires such reports to describe the number, nature, and amount of the awards, the claims involved in the controversy, and any other relevant information that may aid Congress in evaluating the scope and impact of such awards.</p> <p>Directs the Chairman to create and maintain a searchable database on an Internet website containing specified information with respect to each award, including: </p> <ul> <li>if available, the case name and number of, as well as a hyperlink to, any case in which the party other than the agency is not an individual; </li> <li>the name of the agency involved; </li> <li>for an award to an individual, a statement that excludes any personally identifiable information but indicates that the award was made to an individual; </li> <li>for an award made to a party other than an individual, the name of the party;</li> <li>the amount of the award; and</li> <li>the basis for finding that the position of the agency concerned was not substantially justified.</li> </ul> <p>Directs the head of each agency (including, with respect to court cases, the Attorney General [DOJ] and the Director of the Administrative Office of the United States Courts) to provide the Chairman all information requested to produce such reports.</p>]]></text>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Legal fees and court costs</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Law</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <cosponsors />
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssju00</systemCode>
          <name>Judiciary Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on the Judiciary.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <title>Open Book on Equal Access to Justice Act</title>
    <createDate>2014-08-01T10:29:47Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2014-07-31</actionDate>
      <links />
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on the Judiciary.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Law</name>
    </policyArea>
    <billNumber>2770</billNumber>
    <laws />
    <congress>113</congress>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2014-05-07</actionDate>
          <text>Received in the Senate and Read twice and referred to the Committee on the Judiciary.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <type>HR</type>
        <congress>113</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
        <latestTitle>Open Book on Equal Access to Justice Act</latestTitle>
        <number>2919</number>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>ssju00</systemCode>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <subcommittees />
          <name>Judiciary Committee</name>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2014-08-01T01:45:56Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <committeeReports />
    <notes />
    <amendments />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

