<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Commuting</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Transportation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Labor standards</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Life, casualty, property insurance</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Motor carriers</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Motor vehicles</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation employees</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Transportation safety and security</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Wages and earnings</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <introducedDate>2015-07-09</introducedDate>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <firstName>Cory</firstName>
        <party>D</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Booker, Cory A. [D-NJ]</fullName>
        <state>NJ</state>
        <byRequestType />
        <bioguideId>B001288</bioguideId>
        <lastName>Booker</lastName>
        <middleName>A.</middleName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>2194</lisID>
          <bioguideId>B001288</bioguideId>
          <gpoId />
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <notes />
    <relatedBills />
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:09:54Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2015-07-09T20:33:40Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <type>Standing</type>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <createDate>2015-07-10T09:26:21Z</createDate>
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2015-07-09</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation. (Sponsor introductory remarks on measure: CR S5167-5168)</text>
    </latestAction>
    <recordedVotes />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Transportation and Public Works</name>
    </policyArea>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2015-07-09</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>sscm00</systemCode>
          <name>Commerce, Science, and Transportation Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links>
          <link>
            <name>S5167-5168</name>
            <url>https://www.congress.gov/congressional-record/volume-161/senate-section/page/S5167-5168</url>
          </link>
        </links>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Commerce, Science, and Transportation. (Sponsor introductory remarks on measure: CR S5167-5168)</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2015-07-09</actionDate>
        <committee />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <amendments />
    <title>Truck Safety Act</title>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <actionDate>2015-07-09</actionDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2015-11-04T17:26:19Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <updateDate>2015-07-09T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><b>Truck Safety Act </b></p> <p>This bill increases from $750,000 to $1.5 million (adjusted annually for inflation) the minimum level of financial responsibility required to satisfy liability covering public liability, property damage, and environmental restoration for the transportation of property by a commercial motor carrier in the United States or to a place outside the United States. </p>  <p>The Department of Transportation (DOT) must increase, by regulation, the minimum level of financial responsibility for transporting property or passengers if the current amount is insufficient to satisfy liability claims.</p> <p>DOT shall initiate a rulemaking to establish a federal motor vehicle safety standard requiring a motor vehicle with a gross vehicle weight rating greater than 26,000 pounds to be equipped with crash avoidance and mitigation systems. </p> <p>DOT shall finalize regulations to require such a motor vehicle also to be equipped with an electronic control module requiring the speed to be set by the manufacturer at a maximum 70 m.p.h.</p> <p>DOT must ensure that a review is completed on each motor carrier that demonstrates through performance data that it poses the highest safety risk, especially whenever it is among the highest risk carriers for two consecutive months.</p> <p>DOT shall require, with respect to driver compensation, that a motor carrier:</p> <ul> <li> track the on-duty (not driving) time of an employee whose base compensation is calculated in a manner other than an hourly wage and who is required to keep a record of duty status under the hours of service regulations; and </li> <li> separately compensate the employee for any on-duty (not driving) time period at an hourly rate not less than the federal minimum wage rate under the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938.</li> </ul> <p>This compensation requirement, however, shall not apply where employment is governed by a collective bargaining agreement, negotiated by bona fide employee representatives, if the agreement governs, and compensates the employee for, all hours of on-duty (not driving) time. </p> <p>The Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration shall study the effects of excessive commuting on safety and commercial motor vehicle driver fatigue. </p>]]></text>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <laws />
    <billNumber>1739</billNumber>
    <cosponsors />
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Truck Safety Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to increase the minimum levels of financial responsibility for transporting property, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Truck Safety Act</title>
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <version>1.0.0</version>
    <committeeReports />
    <congress>114</congress>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

