<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Science, Technology, Communications</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Administrative law and regulatory procedures</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Civil actions and liability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Competition and antitrust</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Computer security and identity theft</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Criminal investigation, prosecution, interrogation</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Homeland Security</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Evidence and witnesses</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government ethics and transparency, public corruption</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Public-private cooperation</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <introducedDate>2015-02-11</introducedDate>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <firstName>THOMAS</firstName>
        <party>D</party>
        <fullName>Sen. Carper, Thomas R. [D-DE]</fullName>
        <state>DE</state>
        <byRequestType />
        <bioguideId>C000174</bioguideId>
        <lastName>CARPER</lastName>
        <middleName>R.</middleName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>179</lisID>
          <gpoId>8283</gpoId>
          <bioguideId>C000174</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <notes />
    <relatedBills />
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:08:14Z</updateDate>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <subcommittees />
          <type>Standing</type>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2015-02-11T20:21:16Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <createDate>2015-02-12T05:30:27Z</createDate>
    <latestAction>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2015-02-11</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
    </latestAction>
    <recordedVotes />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Science, Technology, Communications</name>
    </policyArea>
    <actions>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2015-02-11</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2015-02-11</actionDate>
      </item>
    </actions>
    <amendments />
    <title>Cyber Threat Sharing Act of 2015</title>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <actionDate>2015-02-11</actionDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <updateDate>2015-02-11T05:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><strong>Cyber Threat Sharing Act of 2015</strong></p> <p>Amends the Homeland Security Act of 2002 to permit private entities to: (1) disclose lawfully obtained cyber threat indicators to a private information sharing and analysis organization and the national cybersecurity and communications integration center (NCCIC); and (2) receive indicators disclosed by private entities, the federal government, or state or local governments.</p> <p>Permits any entity to disclose lawfully obtained indicators to a federal entity for investigative purposes consistent with the lawful authorities of the federal entity.</p> <p>Restricts private entities' use, retention, or further disclosure of cyber threat indicators to purposes relating to information system protection, cyber threat identification or mitigation, or crime reporting.</p> <p>Directs the Department of Homeland Security (DHS) to select through a competitive process a private entity to identify best practices for private information sharing and analysis organizations.</p> <p>Provides liability protections to entities that voluntarily share lawfully obtained indicators with: (1) the NCCIC, or (2) a private information sharing and analysis organization if the organization self-certifies that it has adopted the best practices identified by the DHS-selected private entity.</p> <p>Directs DHS to: (1) designate the NCCIC to receive and disclose threat indicators to federal and nonfederal entities in as close to real time as practicable, and (2) develop a program to support implementation of automated mechanisms for real time sharing.</p> <p>Prohibits a federal entity from using a disclosed indicator as evidence in a regulatory enforcement action against the entity that disclosed the indicator, but allows a federal entity to use disclosed indicators for regulatory enforcement if the information is received by other lawful means.</p> <p>Requires DHS to develop policies for federal entities to:</p> <ul> <li> anonymize and destroy information in a timely manner to limit the acquisition, interception, retention, use, and disclosure of indicators that are likely to identify specific persons;</li> <li> limit reception, use, and retention only to protect information systems or to investigate, prosecute, or otherwise respond to computer crimes, threats of death or serious bodily harm, serious threats to a minor, or attempts or conspiracies to commit such offenses;</li> <li> preserve confidentiality of proprietary information; and</li> <li> penalize federal employees who violate these policies. </li> </ul> <p>Repeals threat indicator sharing procedures established by this Act five years after enactment of this Act.</p> <p>Expresses the sense of Congress that the statement issued by the Department of Justice and the Federal Trade Commission on April 10, 2014, entitled &quot;Antitrust Policy Statement On Sharing Of Cybersecurity Information&quot; provides protections against antitrust concerns for the legitimate sharing of cyber threat indicators. </p>]]></text>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2015-03-03T22:06:05Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <laws />
    <billNumber>456</billNumber>
    <cosponsors />
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Cyber Threat Sharing Act of 2015</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to codify mechanisms for enabling cybersecurity threat indicator sharing between private and government entities, as well as among private entities, to better protect information systems.</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Cyber Threat Sharing Act of 2015</title>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <version>1.0.0</version>
    <committeeReports />
    <congress>114</congress>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

