<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <title>Federal Supervisor Training Act of 2016</title>
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:12:01Z</updateDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <actions>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-12-08</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2016-12-08</actionDate>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
    </actions>
    <committeeReports />
    <relatedBills />
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <createDate>2016-12-09T05:17:03Z</createDate>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <bioguideId>H001069</bioguideId>
        <fullName>Sen. Heitkamp, Heidi [D-ND]</fullName>
        <middleName />
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>2174</lisID>
          <gpoId />
          <bioguideId>H001069</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
        <state>ND</state>
        <firstName>Heidi</firstName>
        <lastName>Heitkamp</lastName>
        <byRequestType />
        <party>D</party>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <congress>114</congress>
    <notes />
    <amendments />
    <calendarNumbers />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Government Operations and Politics</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects />
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <actionDate>2016-12-08</actionDate>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <updateDate>2016-12-08T05:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><b>Federal Supervisor Training Act of 2016</b></p> <p>This bill requires federal agencies to establish supervisor training programs that: (1) require supervisors and management officials to have individual development plans for training on actions, options, and strategies to use for supervisory functions regarding the performance and productivity of agency employees; (2) train supervisors on prohibited personnel practices and employee rights; and (3) provide experienced supervisor mentors to advise new or underperforming supervisors. </p> <p>The bill expands manager training program requirements for employee performance appraisals, mentoring, and management of unacceptable employee performance into mandatory supervisor and manager training programs that also include supervisor training on: </p> <ul> <li>fostering equal opportunities and fairness in the workplace;</li> <li>using probationary periods to examine whether employees are performing at an acceptable level to continue their employment;</li> <li>addressing reports of hostile work environment, retaliation, or harassment;</li> <li>meeting supervisor competencies established by the Office of Personnel Management (OPM) or the employing agency; and</li> <li>collaborating with human resources to recruit, select, appraise, and reward employees based on organizational goals, budget considerations, and staffing needs.</li> </ul> <p>After initial training on each program component, supervisors must complete subsequent training every three years. </p> <p>Agencies must develop a career track for mission critical technical expert employees that affords such employees the opportunity for career advancement without being required to be appointed to a management or supervisory position.</p> <p>The OPM must issue guidance to agencies on competencies supervisors are expected to meet in order to effectively manage the performance of employees. Each agency must assess the performance of supervisors and the overall capacity of its supervisors.</p>]]></text>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2017-02-10T16:19:06Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <recordedVotes />
    <version>1.0.0</version>
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
      <links />
      <actionDate>2016-12-08</actionDate>
    </latestAction>
    <introducedDate>2016-12-08</introducedDate>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>Federal Supervisor Training Act of 2016</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <title>A bill to provide for mandatory training for Federal Government supervisors and the assessment of management competencies.</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <chamberName />
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <title>Federal Supervisor Training Act of 2016</title>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2016-12-08T21:37:09Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <type>Standing</type>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <billNumber>3528</billNumber>
    <laws />
    <cosponsors />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Government Operations and Politics</name>
    </policyArea>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

