<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Improving Veterans Care in the Community Act of 2016</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>A bill to amend title 38, United States Code, to consolidate and expand the provision of health care to veterans through non-Department of Veterans Affairs health care providers, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Improving Veterans Care in the Community Act of 2016</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <amendments />
    <congress>114</congress>
    <committeeReports />
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><strong>Improving Veterans Care in the Community Act of 2016</strong></p> <p>This bill expresses the sense of Congress that: (1) the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) should remain the primary means by which eligible veterans access health care, and (2) the Veterans Health Administration (VHA) needs a simple tool by which it can send veterans into the community to receive health care when appropriate.</p> <p>The bill establishes the Care in the Community Program to furnish specified hospital care and medical services to eligible veterans through certain individuals and entities, including through the use of contracts or agreements. </p> <p>The VA shall: (1) administer the program through its Non-VA Care Coordination Program, and (2) establish an interdisciplinary panel to assist in developing a new clinical appeals process for resolving VA health care disputes.</p> <p>The Government Accountability Office shall report on: (1) clinical operations of the Veterans Health Administration (VHA), (2) the VA travel benefits program, (3) management of the VA's Office of Congressional and Legislative Affairs, and (4) payment by the VA for health care furnished to veterans through non-VA health care providers.</p> <p>The bill repeals specified authorities for emergency treatment reimbursement and contracts for care in non-VA facilities.</p> <p>The bill establishes in the VHA a Payment and Access Commission, which shall: (1) review and make recommendations to Congress regarding VHA policies and regulations affecting veterans health care access, including topics affected by the Care in the Community Program; and (2) create an early-warning system to identify provider shortage areas.</p>]]></text>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <updateDate>2016-09-27T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2017-05-30T18:28:43Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2016-09-27</actionDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <createDate>2016-09-28T05:12:21Z</createDate>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <recordedVotes />
    <policyArea>
      <name>Armed Forces and National Security</name>
    </policyArea>
    <billNumber>3401</billNumber>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects />
        <policyArea>
          <name>Armed Forces and National Security</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:11:54Z</updateDate>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <lastName>CRAPO</lastName>
        <bioguideId>C000880</bioguideId>
        <party>R</party>
        <byRequestType />
        <state>ID</state>
        <firstName>MICHAEL</firstName>
        <fullName>Sen. Crapo, Mike [R-ID]</fullName>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>C000880</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8289</gpoId>
          <lisID>250</lisID>
        </identifiers>
        <middleName>D.</middleName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2016-09-27</actionDate>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <title>Improving Veterans Care in the Community Act of 2016</title>
    <laws />
    <cosponsors />
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-09-27</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssva00</systemCode>
          <name>Veterans' Affairs Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <actionDate>2016-09-27</actionDate>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <notes />
    <introducedDate>2016-09-27</introducedDate>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <version>1.0.0</version>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2016-09-27T20:36:01Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <name>Veterans' Affairs Committee</name>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <subcommittees />
          <systemCode>ssva00</systemCode>
          <type>Standing</type>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <relatedBills />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

