<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <title>Title X Amendments Act of 2016</title>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <laws />
    <billNumber>2818</billNumber>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>Title X Amendments Act of 2016</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>A bill to reduce housing-related health hazards, and for other purposes.</title>
      </item>
      <item>
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <parentTitleType />
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
        <title>Title X Amendments Act of 2016</title>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Housing and Community Development</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Appropriations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Hazardous wastes and toxic substances</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Housing and community development funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Housing supply and affordability</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Low- and moderate-income housing</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <introducedDate>2016-04-19</introducedDate>
    <version>1.0.0</version>
    <cosponsors />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <name>Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee</name>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>ssbk00</systemCode>
          <subcommittees />
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2016-04-19T22:56:05Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-04-19</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>ssbk00</systemCode>
          <name>Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <links>
          <link>
            <url>https://www.congress.gov/congressional-record/volume-162/senate-section/page/S2199</url>
            <name>S2199</name>
          </link>
        </links>
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>0</code>
          <name>Senate</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs. (Sponsor introductory remarks on measure: CR S2199)</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <actionDate>2016-04-19</actionDate>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <code>9</code>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
        </sourceSystem>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Housing and Community Development</name>
    </policyArea>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <committeeReports />
    <createDate>2016-04-20T05:21:44Z</createDate>
    <recordedVotes />
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2016-04-19</actionDate>
      <links />
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs. (Sponsor introductory remarks on measure: CR S2199)</text>
    </latestAction>
    <congress>114</congress>
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:11:04Z</updateDate>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <updateDate>2016-04-19T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <actionDate>2016-04-19</actionDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><b>Title X Amendments Act of 2016</b></p> <p>This bill reauthorizes the Residential Lead-Based Paint Hazard Reduction Act of 1992 and revises the purpose for grants for lead-based paint hazard reduction in target housing.</p> <p>Such grants shall be made instead for reduction of lead-based paint hazards and correction of other housing-related hazards, including any condition of residential real property that poses a risk of biological, physical, radiological, or chemical exposure that can adversely affect human health.</p> <p>The Department of Housing and Urban Development may establish a process by which, in order to verify a family's income level, a grantee may first obtain and use income and program participation information from an entity administering:</p> <ul> <li>the HOME Investment Partnerships program under the Cranston-Gonzalez National Affordable Housing Act;</li> <li>the special supplemental nutrition program for women, infants, and children established under the Child Nutrition Act of 1966;</li> <li>reduced price or free lunches under the Richard B. Russell National School Lunch Act;</li> <li>the weatherization assistance program for low-income persons established under the Energy Conservation and Production Act;</li> <li>the temporary assistance for needy families program under part A of title IV of the Social Security Act (SSAct);</li> <li>the supplemental security income program under SSAct title XVI; or</li> <li>any other program consistent with the family income requirements of the Residential Lead-Based Paint Hazard Reduction Act of 1992.</li> </ul> <p>An Indian tribe and a private nonprofit organization shall be eligible to apply for such a grant, in addition to certain state or local governments, for specified activities relating to lead-based paint hazards.</p> <p>A private nonprofit organization shall also be eligible to apply for a grant to reduce housing-related health hazards.</p> <p>The bill revises grantee selection criteria for a grant to carry out activities relating to lead-based paint hazards, and prescribes criteria for activities relating to housing-related hazards.</p> <p>The bill also prescribes an allocation of funds for grants to assess and correct housing-related health hazards and evaluate the effectiveness of such assessments and corrections. </p>]]></text>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2016-04-27T15:27:30Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <relatedBills>
      <item>
        <type>S</type>
        <latestTitle>True LEADership Act of 2016</latestTitle>
        <latestAction>
          <actionDate>2016-04-20</actionDate>
          <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Finance.</text>
        </latestAction>
        <number>2821</number>
        <congress>114</congress>
        <relationshipDetails>
          <item>
            <type>Related bill</type>
            <identifiedBy>CRS</identifiedBy>
          </item>
        </relationshipDetails>
      </item>
    </relatedBills>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <bioguideId>R000122</bioguideId>
        <party>D</party>
        <firstName>JOHN</firstName>
        <state>RI</state>
        <middleName>F.</middleName>
        <lastName>REED</lastName>
        <byRequestType />
        <fullName>Sen. Reed, Jack [D-RI]</fullName>
        <identifiers>
          <gpoId>8272</gpoId>
          <lisID>949</lisID>
          <bioguideId>R000122</bioguideId>
        </identifiers>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <amendments />
    <notes />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

