<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <introducedDate>2016-05-23</introducedDate>
    <calendarNumbers>
      <item>
        <number>0723</number>
        <calendar>Senate Calendar of Business</calendar>
      </item>
    </calendarNumbers>
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:11:28Z</updateDate>
    <cosponsors />
    <notes />
    <laws />
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2016-12-20</actionDate>
      <text>By Senator Johnson from Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs filed written report under authority of the order of the Senate of 12/10/2016. Report No. 114-407.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <title>GRANT Act</title>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><strong>Grant Reform and New Transparency Act of 2016 or the GRANT Act</strong></p> <p>This bill directs the Office of Management and Budget to upgrade any public website for finding federal grant opportunities to: (1) serve as a central point of information on, and provide full access for applicants to, competitive grants; and (2) capture in one site, or provide electronic links to, other relevant databases.</p> <p>Executive agencies shall post on such website: (1) a clear statement of the purpose, duration, and eligibility requirements of the grant and, for merit-based grants, a description of the manner in which applications or proposals will be evaluated, ranked, and selected; (2) agency contacts and application deadlines; and (3) copies of each proposal that resulted in a grant award, the final grant agreement, and selection documentation and justification. Under certain circumstances, agencies may limit postings to proposal abstracts or executive summaries, redact personally identifiable information, and exclude sensitive information about critical infrastructure.</p> <p>Agencies must evaluate: (1) the ability of the applicant to carry out the grant, manage funds according to accepted cost accounting principles, and comply with federal fund recipient reporting requirements; (2) the past performance and integrity of the applicant; (3) whether the applicant has received other federal funds; and (4) any interagency duplication of efforts for research grants.</p> <p> Agencies must post a forecast of all non-emergency grant solicitations the agency expects to issue for the upcoming calendar year.</p> <p>Upon an applicant's request, an agency must explain the basis for an award decision of a grant exceeding $100,000 pursuant to a merit-based selection procedure.</p> <p>Inspectors General shall review the effectiveness of agency conflicts of interest policy with respect to the peer review process for competitive grants in order to detect favoritism.</p> <p>The Government Accountability Office shall report on the size and training of the federal grants workforce, on whether a warrant system similar to that used in the federal acquisition system should be established for federal officials authorized to award grants, and on recommendations for improving such workforce.</p>]]></text>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <updateDate>2016-05-23T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2016-08-26T19:20:38Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2016-05-23</actionDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
        </item>
        <item>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><strong>Grant Reform and New Transparency Act of 2016 or the GRANT Act</strong></p> <p>(Sec. 2) This bill requires an executive agency, before awarding a competitive grant and after determining eligibility and conducting a merit-based review, to conduct an evaluation of the risk posed by an applicant to successfully carry out the grant. The evaluation shall include a review of any interagency duplication of efforts for research grants.</p> <p>In conducting the evaluation with respect to an applicant that is determined to pose a relatively low risk of failing to execute the grant successfully, an executive agency shall: (1) minimize the burden on the applicant, and (2) consider any existing findings with respect to such applicant under the single audit process.</p> <p>The bill directs the Office of Management and Budget to consult with executive agencies to upgrade grants.gov or any successor public website for finding and applying for federal grants so that the website: (1) serves as a central point of information on, and provides full access for applicants to, competitive grants; and (2) captures in one site, or provides electronic links to, other relevant databases. Executive agencies issuing a solicitation for or announcing the availability of competitive grants shall post on such website: (1) specified information about the grant opportunity, (2) detailed grant guidance and written technical assistance for applicants, and (3) selection documentation and justification. Agencies may redact personally identifiable information from a post on the website and must exclude sensitive information that would adversely affect an applicant. </p> <p>The bill requires each agency to post a forecast of all non-emergency grant solicitations that it expects to issue for the upcoming calendar year. </p> <p>The grants website shall:</p> <ul> <li> make the required information available in its original format without charge or a license or registration requirement;</li> <li> permit the information to be searched, downloaded in bulk, disseminated via automatic electronic means, and freely shared by the public;</li> <li> use permanent uniform resource locators for the information; and</li> <li> provide an opportunity for the public to provide input about the usefulness of the site and recommendations for improvements. </ul> <p>Upon an applicant's request, an agency must explain the basis for an award decision of a grant exceeding $100,000 pursuant to a merit-based selection procedure.</p> <p>Agency inspectors general shall review the effectiveness of an agency's conflicts of interest policy with respect to the peer review process for competitive grants in order to detect favoritism.</p> <p>(Sec. 3) The Government Accountability Office shall report on: (1) the size and training of the federal grants workforce and recommendations for improving it, (2) whether a warrant system similar to that used in the federal acquisition system should be established for federal officials authorized to award grants, and (3) agency use of suspension and debarment actions against grantees during the previous three years and the level of agency resources assigned to suspension and debarment functions.</p>]]></text>
          <actionDesc>Reported to Senate with amendment(s)</actionDesc>
          <updateDate>2016-12-09T17:32:07Z</updateDate>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2017-03-23T18:13:13Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDate>2016-12-09</actionDate>
          <versionCode>01</versionCode>
          <name>Reported to Senate with amendment(s)</name>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <relatedBills />
    <congress>114</congress>
    <version>1.0.0</version>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
          <subcommittees />
          <activities>
            <item>
              <name>Reported by</name>
              <date>2016-12-09T21:00:02Z</date>
            </item>
            <item>
              <name>Markup by</name>
              <date>2016-05-25T14:00:00Z</date>
            </item>
            <item>
              <name>Referred to</name>
              <date>2016-05-23T21:48:23Z</date>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <committeeReports>
      <committeeReport>
        <citation>S. Rept. 114-407</citation>
      </committeeReport>
    </committeeReports>
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Government Operations and Politics</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Congressional oversight</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government employee pay, benefits, personnel management</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government ethics and transparency, public corruption</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Public contracts and procurement</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-12-20</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links>
          <link>
            <name>Report No. 114-407</name>
            <url>https://www.congress.gov/congressional-report/114th-congress/senate-report/407</url>
          </link>
        </links>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>By Senator Johnson from Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs filed written report under authority of the order of the Senate of 12/10/2016. Report No. 114-407.</text>
        <type>Floor</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <links>
          <link>
            <name>Report No. 114-407</name>
            <url>https://www.congress.gov/congressional-report/114th-congress/senate-report/407</url>
          </link>
        </links>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <actionCode>14900</actionCode>
        <type>Committee</type>
        <actionDate>2016-12-20</actionDate>
        <text>By Senator Johnson from Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs filed written report under authority of the order of the Senate of 12/10/2016. Report No. 114-407.</text>
        <committee>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
        </committee>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-12-09</actionDate>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Placed on Senate Legislative Calendar under General Orders. Calendar No. 723.</text>
        <type>Calendars</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-12-09</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs. Reported by Senator Johnson with an amendment in the nature of a substitute. Without written report.</text>
        <type>Committee</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <actionCode>14000</actionCode>
        <type>Committee</type>
        <actionDate>2016-12-09</actionDate>
        <text>Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs. Reported by Senator Johnson with an amendment in the nature of a substitute. Without written report.</text>
        <committee>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
        </committee>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-06-08</actionDate>
        <committee />
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Star Print ordered on the bill.</text>
        <type>Floor</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-05-25</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs. Ordered to be reported with an amendment in the nature of a substitute favorably.</text>
        <type>Committee</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-05-23</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssga00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2016-05-23</actionDate>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>9</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <orderedReported>1</orderedReported>
        <placedOnCalendarGeneralOrders>1</placedOnCalendarGeneralOrders>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
        <committeeFiledReportToAccompany>1</committeeFiledReportToAccompany>
        <reportedToSenate>2</reportedToSenate>
        <senateCommitteeReportFiledAfterReporting>1</senateCommitteeReportFiledAfterReporting>
        <starPrintOrdered>1</starPrintOrdered>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <firstName>James</firstName>
        <bioguideId>L000575</bioguideId>
        <byRequestType />
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>2050</lisID>
          <bioguideId>L000575</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8113</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <fullName>Sen. Lankford, James [R-OK]</fullName>
        <lastName>Lankford</lastName>
        <party>R</party>
        <middleName />
        <state>OK</state>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Government Operations and Politics</name>
    </policyArea>
    <billNumber>2972</billNumber>
    <recordedVotes />
    <cboCostEstimates>
      <item>
        <pubDate>2016-12-08T20:38:00Z</pubDate>
        <url>https://www.cbo.gov/publication/52325</url>
        <title>S. 2972, Grant Reform and New Transparency Act of 2016</title>
      </item>
    </cboCostEstimates>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType>Short Titles Senate</parentTitleType>
        <title>GRANT Act</title>
        <chamberCode>S</chamberCode>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Reported to Senate</titleType>
        <chamberName>Senate</chamberName>
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType>Short Titles Senate</parentTitleType>
        <title>Grant Reform and New Transparency Act of 2016</title>
        <chamberCode>S</chamberCode>
        <titleType>Short Titles as Reported to Senate</titleType>
        <chamberName>Senate</chamberName>
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>GRANT Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Grant Reform and New Transparency Act of 2016</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>A bill to amend title 31, United States Code, to provide transparency and require certain standards in the award of Federal grants, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
      <item>
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>GRANT Act</title>
        <chamberCode />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberName />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <createDate>2016-05-24T05:20:22Z</createDate>
    <amendments />
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

