<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <actions>
      <actionByCounts>
        <houseOfRepresentatives>3</houseOfRepresentatives>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <introducedInTheHouse>1</introducedInTheHouse>
        <billReferrals>1</billReferrals>
        <introducedInHouse>1</introducedInHouse>
      </actionTypeCounts>
      <item>
        <actionCode>H11100</actionCode>
        <actionDate>2015-07-29</actionDate>
        <text>Referred to the House Committee on Financial Services.</text>
        <committee>
          <systemCode>hsba00</systemCode>
          <name>Financial Services Committee</name>
        </committee>
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>House floor actions</name>
          <code>2</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <links />
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>Intro-H</actionCode>
        <actionDate>2015-07-29</actionDate>
        <text>Introduced in House</text>
        <committee />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <links />
      </item>
      <item>
        <actionCode>1000</actionCode>
        <actionDate>2015-07-29</actionDate>
        <text>Introduced in House</text>
        <committee />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <links />
      </item>
    </actions>
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:03:06Z</updateDate>
    <introducedDate>2015-07-29</introducedDate>
    <recordedVotes />
    <createDate>2015-07-30T08:30:35Z</createDate>
    <congress>114</congress>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <firstName>MAXINE</firstName>
        <lastName>WATERS</lastName>
        <state>CA</state>
        <bioguideId>W000187</bioguideId>
        <party>D</party>
        <identifiers>
          <bioguideId>W000187</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>7840</gpoId>
          <lisID>1205</lisID>
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <middleName />
        <fullName>Rep. Waters, Maxine [D-CA-43]</fullName>
        <district>43</district>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Housing and Community Development</name>
    </policyArea>
    <titles>
      <item>
        <title>Moving to Work Reform Act of 2015</title>
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>To provide for extension of agreements between the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development and public housing agencies participating in the Moving to Work Demonstration Program, and for other purposes.</title>
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Moving to Work Reform Act of 2015</title>
        <parentTitleType />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
        <chamberName />
        <chamberCode />
      </item>
    </titles>
    <amendments />
    <version>1.0.0</version>
    <cosponsors>
      <item>
        <state>NY</state>
        <party>D</party>
        <isOriginalCosponsor>True</isOriginalCosponsor>
        <lastName>VELAZQUEZ</lastName>
        <middleName>M.</middleName>
        <district>7</district>
        <fullName>Rep. Velazquez, Nydia M. [D-NY-7]</fullName>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>1184</lisID>
          <bioguideId>V000081</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8073</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <sponsorshipDate>2015-07-29</sponsorshipDate>
        <sponsorshipWithdrawnDate />
        <bioguideId>V000081</bioguideId>
        <firstName>NYDIA</firstName>
      </item>
    </cosponsors>
    <constitutionalAuthorityStatementText><![CDATA[<pre>From the Congressional Record Online through the Government Publishing Office [<a href='http://www.gpo.gov'>www.gpo.gov</a>]By Ms. MAXINE WATERS of California:H.R. 3424.Congress has the power to enact this legislation pursuantto the following:Article I, Section 8, Clause I of the Constitution of theUnited States[Page H5775]</pre>]]></constitutionalAuthorityStatementText>
    <billType>HR</billType>
    <committeeReports />
    <notes />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Employment and training programs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Housing and community development funding</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Low- and moderate-income housing</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Public housing</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Housing and Community Development</name>
        </policyArea>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <subcommittees />
          <type>Standing</type>
          <chamber>House</chamber>
          <name>Financial Services Committee</name>
          <systemCode>hsba00</systemCode>
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2015-07-29T14:06:40Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
    <latestAction>
      <actionDate>2015-07-29</actionDate>
      <text>Referred to the House Committee on Financial Services.</text>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <relatedBills />
    <laws />
    <originChamber>House</originChamber>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <title>Moving to Work Reform Act of 2015</title>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2015-11-04T22:13:57Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in House</actionDesc>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><b>Moving to Work Reform Act of 2015</b></p> <p>This bill prohibits the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) from entering into or extending any Moving to Work agreement for any public housing agency (PHA) for participation in the Moving to Work Demonstration Program, unless the agreement is subject to specified terms and conditions set forth by this Act for its entire duration.</p> <p>(Under the Moving to Work Demonstration Program up to 30 selected PHAs, including Indian housing authorities, may administer the public or Indian housing program and the Section 8 housing assistance payments program in ways designed to reduce costs and achieve greater cost-effectiveness in federal expenditures, provide incentives for heads of households to become economically self-sufficient, and increase housing choices for lower-income families.) <p>Under such an agreement a PHA:</p> <ul> <li> may not establish any new rent policy that raises rent burdens for a significant portion of participating families, or causes specified other results, unless certain conditions are met;</li> <li>may use funds appropriated for renewal of tenant-based rental assistance only for payments assisting eligible families with housing costs;</li> <li> shall receive funding for renewal of tenant-based rental assistance under the same formula applied to nonparticipating PHAs;</li> <li>must provide ongoing housing assistance to substantially the same number of eligible low-income families as it could assist ordinarily but with average cost burdens no higher than those of families assisted under Sections 8 (low-income housing assistance) and 9 (Public Housing Capital and Operating Funds) of the United States Housing Act of 1937; and </li> <li>develop and implement a plan to expand families' access to neighborhoods with low crime, high-performing schools, or other indicators of high opportunity, if a disproportionately low share of PHA-assisted families lives in such neighborhoods. </li> </ul> <p>HUD may not waive specified housing-related requirements.</p> <p>HUD must conduct a comprehensive evaluation of the Demonstration Program to:</p> <ul> <li>analyze the risks and potential benefits of expanding it to additional agencies; and</li> <li>identify reforms, and selection criteria in case the Demonstration Program is expanded, that would improve its effectiveness in testing innovative policies while minimizing adverse effects on low-income families and ensuring efficient use of federal funds to meet the most pressing housing needs.</li> </ul>]]></text>
          <updateDate>2015-07-29T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <name>Introduced in House</name>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDate>2015-07-29</actionDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <calendarNumbers />
    <billNumber>3424</billNumber>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

