<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<billStatus>
  <bill>
    <cosponsors />
    <calendarNumbers />
    <titles>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Veteran Overmedication Prevention Act of 2016</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Short Titles as Introduced</titleType>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>A bill to direct the Secretary of Veterans Affairs to conduct an independent review of the deaths of certain veterans by suicide, and for other purposes.</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Official Title as Introduced</titleType>
      </item>
      <item>
        <chamberCode />
        <parentTitleType />
        <title>Veteran Overmedication Prevention Act of 2016</title>
        <chamberName />
        <titleType>Display Title</titleType>
      </item>
    </titles>
    <cboCostEstimates />
    <originChamber>Senate</originChamber>
    <actions>
      <item>
        <actionDate>2016-09-28</actionDate>
        <committee>
          <name>Veterans' Affairs Committee</name>
          <systemCode>ssva00</systemCode>
        </committee>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Senate</name>
          <code>0</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs.</text>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
      </item>
      <item>
        <links />
        <sourceSystem>
          <name>Library of Congress</name>
          <code>9</code>
        </sourceSystem>
        <actionCode>10000</actionCode>
        <type>IntroReferral</type>
        <actionDate>2016-09-28</actionDate>
        <text>Introduced in Senate</text>
        <committee />
      </item>
      <actionByCounts>
        <senate>2</senate>
      </actionByCounts>
      <actionTypeCounts>
        <referredToCommittee>1</referredToCommittee>
        <introducedInSenate>1</introducedInSenate>
      </actionTypeCounts>
    </actions>
    <notes />
    <committeeReports />
    <updateDate>2017-10-27T18:11:54Z</updateDate>
    <billNumber>3410</billNumber>
    <latestAction>
      <text>Read twice and referred to the Committee on Veterans' Affairs.</text>
      <actionDate>2016-09-28</actionDate>
      <links />
    </latestAction>
    <version>1.0.0</version>
    <introducedDate>2016-09-28</introducedDate>
    <sponsors>
      <item>
        <identifiers>
          <lisID>754</lisID>
          <bioguideId>M000303</bioguideId>
          <gpoId>8253</gpoId>
        </identifiers>
        <byRequestType />
        <party>R</party>
        <bioguideId>M000303</bioguideId>
        <state>AZ</state>
        <firstName>JOHN</firstName>
        <lastName>MCCAIN</lastName>
        <middleName>SIDNEY</middleName>
        <fullName>Sen. McCain, John [R-AZ]</fullName>
      </item>
    </sponsors>
    <billType>S</billType>
    <createDate>2016-09-29T05:34:47Z</createDate>
    <relatedBills />
    <subjects>
      <billSubjects>
        <policyArea>
          <name>Armed Forces and National Security</name>
        </policyArea>
        <legislativeSubjects>
          <item>
            <name>Department of Veterans Affairs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Drug therapy</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Drug trafficking and controlled substances</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Drug, alcohol, tobacco use</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government information and archives</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Government studies and investigations</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health facilities and institutions</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Health information and medical records</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Hospital care</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Medicaid</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Medical research</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Medical tests and diagnostic methods</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Mental health</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Neurological disorders</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Prescription drugs</name>
          </item>
          <item>
            <name>Veterans' medical care</name>
          </item>
        </legislativeSubjects>
      </billSubjects>
    </subjects>
    <title>Veteran Overmedication Prevention Act of 2016</title>
    <summaries>
      <billSummaries>
        <item>
          <name>Introduced in Senate</name>
          <updateDate>2016-09-28T04:00:00Z</updateDate>
          <versionCode>00</versionCode>
          <actionDesc>Introduced in Senate</actionDesc>
          <actionDate>2016-09-28</actionDate>
          <text><![CDATA[<p><strong>Veteran Overmedication Prevention Act of 2016</strong></p> <p>This bill requires the Department of Veterans Affairs (VA) to contract with the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (or another private, not-for-profit entity with comparable expertise) to review the deaths of all covered veterans who died by suicide during the last five years.</p> <p>The review shall include:</p> <ul> <li>the total numbers of veterans who died by a violent death or by an accidental death during such period;</li> <li> each veteran's age, gender, race, and ethnicity;</li> <li>a list of medications and substances prescribed to such veterans, as annotated on toxicology reports;</li> <li>a summary of medical diagnoses by VA physicians that led to such prescriptions in cases of anxiety and depressive disorders;</li> <li>the number of instances in which such a veteran was concurrently on multiple medications prescribed by VA physicians;</li> <li>the number of such veterans who were not taking any VA-prescribed medication;</li> <li> the percentage of such veterans treated for anxiety or depressive disorders who received a non-medication first-line treatment compared to the percentage who received medication only;</li> <li> the number of instances in which a non-medication first-line treatment was attempted and deemed ineffective which led to prescribing medication;</li> <li>descriptions of how the VA determines and updates clinical practice guidelines for prescribing medications and of VA efforts to maintain appropriate staffing levels for mental health professionals;</li> <li>the percentage of such veterans with combat experience or related trauma; </li> <li>identification of VA medical facilities with markedly high prescription rates and suicide rates for treated veterans;</li> <li> an analysis of VA programs that collaborate with state Medicaid agencies and the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services;</li> <li> an analysis of VA medical center collaboration with medical examiners' offices or local jurisdictions to determine veteran mortality and cause of death;</li> <li>identification of a best practice model to collect and share veteran death certificate data;</li> <li>an assessment of any apparent patterns based on the review; and</li> <li>recommendations to improve the safety and well-being of veterans. </li> </ul> <p>The VA shall ensure that such data is compiled in a manner that allows it to be analyzed across all data fields for purposes of informing and updating VA clinical practice guidelines.</p> <p>A &quot;covered veteran&quot; means any veteran who received VA hospital care or medical services during the five-year period preceding the veteran's death.]]></text>
          <lastSummaryUpdateDate>2016-12-15T22:45:32Z</lastSummaryUpdateDate>
        </item>
      </billSummaries>
    </summaries>
    <policyArea>
      <name>Armed Forces and National Security</name>
    </policyArea>
    <laws />
    <recordedVotes />
    <congress>114</congress>
    <amendments />
    <committees>
      <billCommittees>
        <item>
          <name>Veterans' Affairs Committee</name>
          <subcommittees />
          <activities>
            <item>
              <date>2016-09-28T17:04:36Z</date>
              <name>Referred to</name>
            </item>
          </activities>
          <chamber>Senate</chamber>
          <type>Standing</type>
          <systemCode>ssva00</systemCode>
        </item>
      </billCommittees>
    </committees>
  </bill>
  <dublinCore xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
    <dc:language>EN</dc:language>
    <dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
    <dc:contributor>Congressional Research Service, Library of Congress</dc:contributor>
    <dc:description>This file contains bill summaries and statuses for federal legislation. A bill summary describes the most significant provisions of a piece of legislation and details the effects the legislative text may have on current law and federal programs. Bill summaries are authored by the Congressional Research Service (CRS) of the Library of Congress. As stated in Public Law 91-510 (2 USC 166 (d)(6)), one of the duties of CRS is "to prepare summaries and digests of bills and resolutions of a public general nature introduced in the Senate or House of Representatives". For more information, refer to the User Guide that accompanies this file.</dc:description>
  </dublinCore>
</billStatus>

